welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
oh okay check-ins Oh nervous maybe like
47% drinking espresso right now so that
could have something to do with it other
than that I feel a sense of readiness so
welcome to the stoah I am Peter
Lindbergh the Stewart of the stoah and
the stole is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge at this moment and we
might have some new faces here so I'll
just give some background on what I see
the stove becoming so there's three
aspects to it one is a wisdom gym that's
being cultivated by the collective
intelligence or the people who are drawn
to this space and we have a lot of kind
of sexy and unpredictable psycho
technologies like existential dance
parties or cretak speed-dating an emetic
mediation the boot camps and stuff like
that
and I'm also using this as a place are
seeing this as a place for an incubator
for psycho technology so if people want
to experiment with different sort of
transfer transformational experiences on
zoom' I'm handing them the keys and
letting them sort of mess up in the wise
way and the last category I see is
inviting kind of really important sense
making nodes that I see in the noosphere
sort of like renegade intellectuals like
true thinkers to invite them in this
space to share their thoughts at the
knife's edge and to allow the collective
intelligence to ask them the right
question and that's what we're here
today with Dave Snowden so with that
being said we have everyone's favorite
philosopher queen raven connelly is
going to be leading a she's gonna
introduce Dave and she's going to lead
the Q&A and so I'll hand it over to her
but first I have to allow everyone to
unmute themselves you can unmute
yourself now great good morning so today
we have Dave Snowden the founder and
chief scientific officer of the
cognitive edge his work has been
influential on game be
thinkers and people all over the world
and he's covered
he's pioneered a science-based approach
to organizations drawing on anthropology
neuroscience and complex adaptive
adaptive Systems Theory so we're super
excited to hear from him today we're
gonna have about 20 to 25 minutes of
Dave talking on a on a given subject and
then we'll move over to Q&A so you can
put your questions in the chat and then
I will call on you and you can unmute
yourself and ask your question and with
that Dave okay
he's probably down there in the lion's
den there's some do use a materialist a
realist and a cynic as opposed to a
stoic but um so I'll kind of like go
with this as we come just to give by way
of background my original degree was
physics and philosophy as a joint major
Matt himself was contentious I story
because I was at university in the 70s
and I still remember my first essay came
back with this isn't philosophy this is
metaphysics
please rewrite it and I send it back
with metaphysics his philosophy please
mark it and we carried on like that for
three years yeah
this was the British analytical
tradition in philosophy and I still
remember proposing that we have a course
on existentialism and B there was a
student rep on the committee and the
professor in charge of the department
said if I wanted to study European
literature there was another college for
that right so come like that's
entertaining right but what it told me
is two things I got away with that
because you know there were all sorts of
other things going in in background in
the seventies you could get away with
things at university yeah if you were
interesting people come like gave you
aids on essays just because you woke
them up because they weren't mark into a
you know writing marking to Martin plan
but the physics also gave me a sort of
natural respect for Natural Science but
physics is actually quite good on that
because he carries with it in essential
paradox between general relativity
theory and quantum mechanics which come
I both work but which contradict each
other
so between that and philosophy you get
very comfortable with paradox yeah and
with uncertainty either way that worked
I then spent three years of my life
you know there is the gallivanting
around Australia Africa Latin America
are on the wheel Council of Churches
program to combat racism which kind of
like shook me up a hell of a lot I saw
the first person murdered in front of me
and in Australia when a mine guard came
out and literally shot an Aboriginal
activist and killed him I'll never
forget two of us
yeah we're young all right we went to
the police and the police said it's only
in a bow and when we protested took us
out of territory but the scary thing is
nobody in geneva would listen to us and
kind of like my kids cannot forget that
I mean in the 70s Catholics didn't have
the vote in Northern Ireland and I'll
never forget encounters with the Stasi
in East Berlin and kind of like it was
the world was an interesting place where
we say I mean the way after that I ended
up in the early days of computing and I
became a decision support specialist I
then migrated through that after - soft
internal software startups into a
strategy role and then in my 20 odd
years ago
IBM bought the company and I got given a
creative role my just done a major
turnaround and booked together different
disciplines so I got one of those jobs
which is do whatever you want as long as
it's interesting and will pay you a
salary so I survived seven years there
right and it was 7 months for the
Jesuits in seven years with IBM but
that's a different level of maturity
before I finally failed the test of
obedience you know in both cases and
that's when I got into complexity theory
and narrative because we were looking at
how do people make decisions and we knew
that the dominant method by which people
people make decisions is something
called conceptual blending so the way
you make a decision is you scan about 5%
of what's available to you on a good day
if you're Chinese it doubles and there
are various reasons for that and then
you do a first fit pattern match with
multiple fragmented memories
and you blend those to come up get
together to come up with a unique form
of action so kind of like that got us
into gathering people's stories to find
out not only when they made decisions
but how they made decisions and not to
do it as an expert in a workshop but to
get people to keep their own Diaries and
interpret their own experiences and
that's translated into the modern what
we do which is actually all about what's
called epistemic justice which is
allowing people to the in to be the
interpreters of their narrative rather
than the experts then I'll come back to
that towards the end and I talked about
Kovac
so that was critical and the other thing
you started to learn them when we were
dealing with knowledge and organizations
inherent uncertainty that got me into
complexity science I spent a lot of time
on that and come like in classic mode I
decided that the complexity science then
was moving to entirely agent based
models so the whole idea was simulation
models big data I was very nervous about
that because I had this fundamental
belief that human beings aren't ants
yeah
to me this is self-evident that most
social scientists it isn't because their
models don't work unless they make that
assumption so human beings have
intelligence they have flexible identity
they have empathy there are all sorts of
factors which make human beings an extra
level of complexity so that got me to
where I am now which is a synthesis of
the biological end of anthropology
cognitive neuroscience the whole bunch
of delusion epistemology which is
actually relevant to narrative and of
course complexity science and that feels
cool down through complexity and to
distinguish it and I'll give some
examples and sort of projects I think
the other things which come out of that
and I just want to do a sort of 101 take
on this from a complexity point of view
in a complex adaptive system what
matters isn't individuals but how
they're entangled it's the connections
between things which matter and the
trouble with the northern European North
American agenda for the
what ever since the Reformation as its
focused entirely on the individual and
the assumption that society and
communities are aggregations of
individual behavior and individual
interest whereas if you go to Africa or
Asia or the southern southern Europe or
the Celtic fringe of Britain those
communities are calm you terian that
they're defined by their interactions
not by who you are and complexity is
backing that up which means all of the
Western focus on change in resilience
has been about individual meditation
individual resilience actually isn't
that effective
it's a culturally specific thing what
really matters is who and how you
interact with and there's all sorts of
things we can draw from example the
Army's use of crews in that area so
interactions are key and the
entanglement concept is also vital to
understand so lysse Gerardo is one of
the best thinkers here famously
described complexity is like bramble
bushes in a thicket so you've got you
know it produces fruit but you can't
untangle it is the entanglement has
evolved over time other types of
entanglement is where we work on
software so for example we'll take a
patient's observes narratives on a
continuous timeline the nurses observed
narratives their relatives observed
narratives and will entangle them at
different levels of coherence in order
to understand different patterns about
what's going on within those community
you know talk about more that if you
want but entanglement is how things are
linked then connecting and how you focus
on that for change so support groups are
key and part of the problem we got would
lock them is that people are divorced
from social interaction and just to
throw some other science in on this part
of the problem you've got with zoom one
of the ways to stay healthy was zoom by
the way is to switch off video for at
least half of your calls because we've
got three generations of radio and
telephone you know which means the
epigenetics is coming to play after two
generations so we're comfortable with
abstracted voice without human contact
but if we see somebody's picture we
expect chemical responses as well for
example their affair and then pick up
sticks we trust and our body and brain
don't get those so we get very confused
now particularly when we see in multiple
pictures so sorry that was just a little
sideline on that so complexity is about
entanglement it's about linking and
connecting things in different ways it's
about creating resilience which isn't
robustness and this is come at this key
distinction I want to make between a
resilient system and a robust system and
I should say now that I'm not using this
language in the way that Nicholas Taleb
works it I'm part of an on a group of
people who've been blocked by talent I
think if you've got any confidence
you're blocked
because he doesn't tolerate dissent yeah
I got there with a few Nobel Prize
winners so I feel happy about it
yeah so what Tyler tried to do with anti
fragile is basically try and create
something unique which actually isn't
unique now from my perspective the
system which gets stronger when it's
threatened is just a type of resilience
it's a symbiosis for example is a good
example of that but if you want to
publish a popular management book every
two years you could have claimed
something highly original otherwise it
doesn't sell says he's slightly
cynically yeah so I'm using language
differently as the point I want to make
so a resilient system is one which
survives with continuity of identity
over time turn back to that identity
were yeah so my best metaphor for this
is to think about a robust system as a
seawall so you've got this massive thing
of concrete or whatever you can drain
the land on the landward side you can
plant crops it's wonderful until the
design conditions are exceeded and the
seawall breaks then it would be better
if it wasn't there at all so robust
systems are characterized by certainty
but catastrophic results when they break
doesn't mean they're wrong it just means
you need to realize that on the other
hand a resilient system is a salt marsh
so basically the sea comes in it floods
the land
yeah the land is constantly changing to
accommodate different flow
patterns when the land is saturated it
will still flood beyond the salt marsh
but the salt marsh doesn't release the
water which is already stored yeah so
the changes in catastrophic so that's a
really important distinction the other
key aspect which thinks in with this is
a concept of constraints in convexity
theory and the distinction between
enabling constraints in governing
constraints so governing constraints
provide boundaries that you can measure
in which you can know they can be
permeable a non permeable but they
constitute a barrier yeah a container
where as enabling constraints how things
connect and the connections are there to
optimize energy flow so if you want to
change a system you have to change the
energy gradient so that the change you
want is more likely you won't achieve
change against the natural energy
gradient and a complex system is
dispositional not causal there's been a
couple of minutes on this physics
critical so in a complex adaptive system
you have no linear material causality
because there are too many changes in
too many sort of things going on
continuously we have things like dark
constraints as a reference to dark
energy in cosmology we can see the
impact of a constraint that we can't see
what the constraint is so we got
inherent uncertainty but we can measure
disposition allottee and that's the work
we do with distributed ethnography but
if you don't have causality you can't
actually have goals because you can't
predict the future so the key is to
understand about complexity and this
highly contrast with systems thinking
because systems thinking assumes
causality it comes from cybernetics
they're kinda mental thing about
complexity is you start journeys with a
sense of direction but you don't try and
achieve goals because if you start a
journey with a sense of direction you
move to what's called an adjacent
possible you find somewhere where you
can go next which is in roughly the
right direction then you reassess and
now that's for that
and I'll talk about how we do that
that's where we get into the distributed
ethnography so we worked on this for
some years and yeah I'll talk about the
background to this it originally came
from working DARPA so we were looking at
counterterrorism I it was a bit of a
shock I was working for IBM you know and
just so the way you know of my
background I come from a Catholic
Marxist background so that that's my 70s
so to get asked to go down to Langley
was a bit of a shock right but either
way it got interesting we did a huge
amount of work before and after 9/11 and
what we're looking for is how do you
find weak signals so how do you find
when a civilian population yet has got
to a point of despair to the point where
it allowed terrorists to intrude
now I remember this my ownself from
1970s when I was in Northern Ireland and
I still remember the night when I was
walking down the Falls Road and I got
picked up by the police yeah and in a
Catholic area I got picked up by the
police for a Protestant and asked which
of my legs did I want shot off first and
then they hit my accent and realized I
was mainland Catholic not Irish Catholic
because I wasn't a filthy take
quote/unquote so they extremely asked
the Land Rover it was hidden what the
trouble now if the Provisional IRA
commander had come round that night I'd
have probably joined yeah luckily he
didn't write you know everything is
small things producing maximum facts so
and if you actually what happened in the
land and the Catholic population wasn't
happy about British occupation but it
was okay with it until Bloody Sunday
then it went the other way from that
point onwards nobody in the population
would go into a police station he just
wouldn't go in in terms of the way it
worked and there was a whole bunch of
peace and reconciliation work but the
most interest in the way we approached
it was to actually take people from both
communities and dumped them in Latin
America for six months and not talk
about the troubles whereas the other
guys got everybody together in a big
room and got them all to agree how they
would all love each other and all would
be nice and they didn't want to have
conflict if anybody's seen a wonderful
comedy from Northern Ireland called
Derry girls
is satirized in the first episode of the
second series yeah basically they all
agreed not to do anything nasty but
within three days they were doing nasty
things to each other again
because nobody had changed the social
and economic context yeah what we did if
you look at it we threw people away an
asymmetric groups we actually meant that
they interacted with each other in a
hostile situation so they saw they had
more in common than they had in DIF and
that was one example but all we now do
is for example get children from schools
to go into their community and act as
ethnographers to gather stories from
that community the way we normally start
with that is go to adults in your
community the view most respect and ask
them from the story of their life that
they think you should remember these are
called sacred stories and anthropology
and then what we basically do is to get
them to self interpret their own stories
now this is the epistemic justice issue
it's the power issue because if you hand
your stories over to a researcher
paralysing who interprets a story not in
the story as it was told so we transfer
that power back into the community and
that then allows us effectively what we
got is a quantitative technique in what
is traditionally a qualitative domain so
we can scale in real time and so we can
draw a Fitness landscapes which look
like contour maps in fact it's probably
easy to show you one okay you disabled
screen-sharing guys if you enable screen
sharing I can show something yeah so a
fitness landscape comes from
evolutionary biology so what it allows
so that this is an example of one it's
probably better so this is a fitness
landscape yeah that's got about four or
five thousand stories in it so people
have interpreted their own stories into
a framework this and these are not
Likert scales our own gamble and this is
a probability distribution in this
particular case we presented a common
problem to a
large number of people we've got them
all to interpret that problem and then
we draw a map of how different groups
interpret the data in different ways so
you can see if you look at this there's
this sort of red group who sort of stand
alone they got no overlap with the blue
group yeah so there's no chance of them
having a conversation
yeah the overlap groups can have
conversations with each other and this
is a key concept which we measure called
coherent heterogeneity this is actually
quite a healthy picture yeah you've got
overlaps between most groups but you've
got enough difference in the system and
the system can evolve but if you want to
change the system so for example that
blue stuff at the bottom is too extreme
and so let's suppose that the bottom
left is where you don't want to be the
top right is the direction you want to
travel what you can actually do on this
is you can click on the bottom blue bit
and you can see the stories which make
up the pan and then you can say we want
fewer stories like this what would we do
you can click on the purple bit which is
going in the right direction that's an
adjacent possible and you can say what
could we do tomorrow to create more
stories like this now that's a whole new
theory of change more stories like these
fewer stories like that when we work in
patient safety if you say how do we make
the environment safer people say but we
already are safe if you actually show
them patient stories and say we want
more stories like this and fewer stories
like that
nobody is threatened by the request and
you get much more interested in gaygent
now I'm using this because this is key
to resilience a system which has
difference in it but it can come here
when it needs to is resilient a system
where everybody believes and thinks the
same way is not resilient because it's
homogeneous it lacks efficient variety
and the way I normally illustrate this
in this lecture the other day is I know
I'm Welsh right you need to understand
that now you understand that
we'll largely defined by not being
English right this is important so we
have four rugby teams
my hobby is a rugby an opera and by the
way we sing at rugby matches we're a
choral nation so I've got a real problem
with kovat because my two main hobbies
aren't available to me but when I go
much tardis please play rugby that's my
team there are four teams in South Wales
yeah I wear my blue costume yeah I've
got my Sita I've had for the last 40
years I sit in it my mother had it
before me
Cardiff if you don't know it a really
good team full of high integrity players
who never treat never commit violence
and I generally put upon by the other
teams or a bunch of horrendous cheats
particularly those bastards from
fanatically here you can't trust yeah so
we have a lot of rivalry on this but
when the English arrived were Welsh no
that's coherent heterogeneity difference
in one context commonality in another
context yeah so that's kind of one of
the key things and we use these maps to
actually measure resilience within a
community yeah and actually identify
pathways of change so that's one other
aspect of the work the other is I'm
currently right in the EU handbook on
how to manage complexity and chaos which
I've got to get back to this evening
because it needs to get out next week
and there's a couple of key lapses in
that I wanted to highlight on how do you
create resilience in society and one of
the key rules is you distribute
decision-making but you centralized
coordination generally organizations get
that wrong and they centralized
decision-making and assume the system
will coordinate any can't yeah but you
don't distribute decision-making them
just by saying we'll trust people you
create processes which naturally
generate trust so the army do this for
example they have what are called crews
now same with firefighters so people are
trained in roll and roll expectation
entry into the cruel is ritualized we
changes your identity so a crew has
cognitive capacity more than the sum of
the parts but it will actually behave in
a consistent way so you can delegate to
a crew and not worry about it we're
creating temporary cruising Co vids so
for example triage decisions which are
really scary at the moment we can say
well any doctor can make any decision
where the situation is ambiguous
provided it's signed off by a nurse from
another ward an administrator who spends
five minutes checking it you said I've
done I've created a threeway process
which says you'll have to be transparent
to a degree and you have to be validated
I'm not just trusting you to make the
decisions but you don't have to refer
upwards you know there's other methods
on that so a distributed decision-making
central coordination is key the other is
a crisis is a major opportunity for
learning and innovation so we're
actually starting now to get leaders to
collect and also people in across the
organization to capture fragmented
learning in journals throughout the day
the morning and evening reflection the
ability a missed opportunity thing that
I've observed of the innovation
possibility and part of that's
increasing resilience within families
and organizations because if you're
engaged in the tasks related to the
problem you have a sense of purpose if
you're just the recipient of
communication you don't have that
purpose anymore you're a suffering
massive socialization and there's no
related project I'm very proud of the
one we did in Rwanda well we got young
girls who've being genetically mutilated
and raped to actually act as
ethnographers to people at risk of the
same horror in their own community and
what was interesting there is that was
better therapy than being counseled
about the problem yeah going to do
something human beings are action based
so starting to create mechanisms by
which communities engage with each other
and actually see themselves as part of
the solution is one of the other ways
that you actually create that sort of
resilience within a system and kind of
like to finish off on this
well if we're launching tomorrow is a
mass narrative micro scenario generation
of post pandemic futures that's been
done with the UN yeah that's a one-week
trial if that works we're gonna go on a
wider um you know regular course every
week you know to try and find attitudes
now that's important for a whole bunch
of reasons so I'm going to get political
for a minute right there's a dominant
trope which has been established by the
populist governments in the UK US and
Brazil yeah which is international
organizations or evil and suck our money
away from us that's called a trope in
narrative the I don't buy memes yeah
it's a pattern of narrative which
creates like a whirlpool effect anybody
in Toulouse this is an assemblage if
you're into complexity it's a strange
attractor and so what's actually
happening now and we can see it in the
UK in the u.s. is an attempt to deflect
blame for the lack of planning on to the
wh oh yeah it's a ready victim and the
reality is certainly and I know in the
US and the UK we're not dealing with a
Black Swan just to be nice to taro we're
dealing with a blank elephant yeah that
means it's a Black Swan it's totally
unexpected but it's the elephant in the
room we knew it was going to happen we
just wanted to ignore it yes so Britain
did a major simulation two years ago on
a flu pandemic which predicted
everything which is happening though but
the government actually haven't read the
report yeah didn't implement the results
and sucked the money away for brexit so
we got this political situation where
we've got a huge opportunity to change
the way we think about society but
what's actually going to happen if we
don't watch it is the blame game will
start to move in a different direction
but it seems to me that the major
opportunity provided by the crisis is
the fact that we now know that money
isn't a rationing device so our former
prime minister in the UK once said when
people wanted to properly fund health
care for the Americans in the audience
you have my sympathy I mean you spend
more per head on public health than
anybody in Europe and you still have you
can't manage for you at the point
of entry health care that's another
issue she said there isn't a magic money
tree well at the moment governments are
growing magic money forests all over the
world
yeah but money is not a rationing device
right money was oh and I think one of
the key things and that's why I don't
buy things like blockchain the problem
is once you have a means of exchange
ownership of the means of exchange is
the most important thing it doesn't
matter that that's actually where
control comes some of the work I did in
cockatoo in Australia in the 70s was to
look at gifting cultures because
indigenous cultures gift and gifting is
not an exchange it's a membership fee
now we can already see gifting happening
in communities around kovat it's not
barter you're not saying I'll do this
and you do the equipment for me
downstream you're saying we're part of
this community which faces a common
front we all do something and then we're
part of the community but if you don't
do anything you're actually excluded
from it so I think there's a really big
opportunity here to look at look at this
there's there's absolutely no reason why
we can't give free at the point of entry
health care and education to everybody
worldwide it's just we choose to ration
it the money and now we know that money
isn't necessarily a rationing device if
you have the right sort of situation to
deal with it the other thing I think
we're starting to realise is that the
supply chains are actually hardly
vulnerable because they lack resilience
they lack they lack time we used to have
four weeks supply of food in the UK
we've got currently got two weeks and so
the process reengineering generation of
the last three three decades has focused
on efficiency at the cost of
effectiveness so building redundancy
back into our systems is also going to
be key downstream and I think people can
now see the advantage of that but the
third thing I think is also to recognize
that we've lost resilience as a society
so I was working with CDC a few years
ago and I remember one of them space
that he said look if we have a really
hard
heart pandemic is probably the over 40's
who will survive not the under forties
it would now be over 50s and I said why
he said because your generation had all
the childhood diseases and quite high
infant mortality and I'm going to be a
bit brutal now if infant mortality falls
below a certain level the species loses
resilience so I have measles German
measles mumps scarlet fever
I had the whole bloody thing they just
went through school as they happen and
also we had social resilience because we
had to play with the Weber's on the
street now my kids have grown up in a
completely clean environment yeah and
they've had very few of the diseases
because of university inoculation I'm
not saying we don't do that I'm not one
of those guys all right but they've
never had that sort of encounter and
also they've been moved between houses
in cars so they only play with safe
people and this was driven home to me in
Los Angeles a few years back so my son
was then 11 and we had a sort of
father-son trip around California for
three weeks you know two nights in
different motels
yeah Grand Canyon the deserts majare via
search we had a great time and at the
end of it we got to Los Andes Airport at
9 o'clock in the morning because I'd
done it on air miles so this was a treat
for him his business class but we'd have
to go to New York five hours in the
lounge and then back to the UK and the
American Airlines attendant said well
why are you doing this there's a direct
flight this evening I can put you both
in first-class yeah he was charming
those things he was a charming 11 year
old so he's very useful right and so we
had an extra day and we went to the Tar
Pits and walking back from the Tar Pits
I suddenly realized we got into a bad
area I mean there's a fewer run the Tar
Pits now because when I was growing up I
knew how to walk and not be noticed
because that was a survival technique
when you walk to school my son has got
on no idea but I'm walking confidently
and my son is saying dad dad we're lost
can we ask for help and I'm saying shut
up Hugh and just walk is he housing up
there's basic instincts so I think one
of the things we've got to start to look
at
is how do we build resilience for threat
right and this is going to be depressing
end point I mean I said the other day on
one call Cove it is sort of God's gift
to humanity because it's a chance to
sort ourselves out yeah it's probably
gonna kill about 10 percent of the
population over two to three years if
you take all the other things but he's
only got a two to three-week gestation
period it's mutating faster than we'd
like so it might be more scary but what
happens if we get something with an 80%
kill rate in a six week gestation period
and then this global warming so the big
thing for me is how do we now create
resilience in the system how do we
create diversity in the system so that
we've got the ability to actually
survive yeah and change things and that
I think it's about the time I was
allocated so I'll stop at that point
excellent thank you so if people would
like to put their their questions in the
chat and then I will call on you and you
can unmute yourself and just initially
Dave I was wondering so there's a term
that's used often in the game be
community in at large which is
sense-making and I noticed that your
software is named sense maker I was
wondering if you could talk about your
understanding of that word and also
maybe explain a little bit about how
your software works I'm actually
currently writing an article on that
publication recently said there are five
schools of sense-making
now and I'm one of them Mike is another
Klein is another Devon is another and
then there's an IT group i define
sense-making which i use a hyphen on
because I don't like neologisms yeah so
it sounds making for me is how do I make
sense of the world so that I can act in
it and so it has with it a concept of
sufficiency is how do I know enough to
act yeah contrast fairly heavily with
Karl Weick so Vikas is a classic
American sociologists economists he
studies cases and he derives general
theory from that
yeah the way I approach it is we don't
use cases because I'm a physicist
no social scientists is ever that have
enough data to form any valid conclusion
whatsoever so what we do is we say what
do we know from cognitive neuroscience
what do we know from complexity science
that acts as a constraint and we build
methods and tools consistent with
natural science so we don't use cases so
that's kind of like a different approach
the way a sense maker works is probably
the easier illustration you've all done
an employee satisfaction survey at some
time in your lives so you get a survey
and it comes round it says don't your
manager consult you on a regular basis
scale of 0 not at all 10 all the time no
now you know exactly what answer they
want because you've got a hypothesis
base question and in evaluative yeah
like let's go we don't do that we say
what story would you tell your best
friend if they were off the job in your
work group yeah or one of the ones we
used in military a lot is imagine you're
a grandparent your grandchild says they
want to join the Marines won't you tell
them
yeah that's an on hypothesis question
and then we get people to self interpret
that and there are various ways we do it
but one is a series of triangles and one
of the triangles for example says in
this story the managers behavior was
altruistic assertive analytical so those
are three positive qualities no this is
all derived from theory in the field so
it's just like longitudinal research
there's a theory in now what happens to
the brain when it sees three positive
qualities is it doesn't know what the
right answer is so it switches from
autumn of it to novelty receptive mode
what cardamon called thinking slow not
thinking fast but that's not as good as
a science yeah so basically we're six
triangles people will spend time
positioning they're dots on the triangle
because that's what this story means and
of course that gives us data points
where no one's were using impatient
journey and actually allowing patients
to tell stories is a power issue as well
it's a sense of agency in their journey
we have a pain empathy scale
and they place markers on that to say
this is how I see things this is how I
think the nurse sees like these things
this is how I think the doctor sees IV
things and of course we can compare that
with a nurse record so there's a medium
article I can send you a link to by an
anthropologist to work for Nokia it was
basically argue in the case for
anthropology so as you said you have big
data which is huge volumes of data and
to my mind a frequent confusion of
correlation with causation I think this
is part of the problem with talib at the
moment alibies running a theme which
says talib is the only one who
understands Kovac he's just running
mathematical models the epidemiologists
are screaming because he doesn't know
how to build the assumptions in right
yeah and that's a trouble we got these
kids
yeah and or people who think I'm a
brilliant statistician I can use
algorithms on available data
the reality is epidemiologists know how
to build those models okay I'm sorry I
shouldn't get on that rant because I
know again that I'm losing the track
where I was going on this so either way
so um so basically what Big Data which
is high volume the black box then you've
got thick data which is ethnography but
of course the ethnographer has to get
stories they can't deal with anecdotes
because they need to actually stimulate
stuff they can interpret and that's low
volume we can use anecdote because
people self interpret their own
anecdotes so we can go to high volume so
typically somebody puts in a picture
voice text any combination that's called
a sense making item you can all play
with this on the leadership journal next
week if you want to play with it you
then interpret it on to a series of
triangles that means I've got 2030 data
points and from that I can draw the sort
of probability maps I'll show you
earlier and it means I can scale them I
wrote a blog post on this I can send you
the link um so that's how the software
works
so it's either to journal to capture or
what I showed you earlier which is to
present data for everybody to interpret
and then look at differences cool and
then you said that there were five
schools of sense-making
you remind us what actually tied you
that my study okay there's an article in
epic which is the yeah ethnography an
industry so it's six of April 2015 by
Peter Hayward and it basically
identifies it's got the nice two-by-two
matrix all right collective individual
internal external I've never bought that
by the way I think it's false humanism
but I'll live with it
so basically at certainly individual is
Gary Klein yeah he was a good friend
I've done a lot of work with him
published with him branded Irving in
internal individual if you've never met
Brenda she's just a wonderful woman I
mean South cured cancer
she's post modernist information science
and you've got Vikas social activity
collective internal and then you've got
Russell Hotel which is collective
external which is data a meaning and
then the pictures got me in the middle
so I quite like it which it basically
has understanding about yeah so that's
the cool paper great thank you so we
have another question from the chat to
what extent do we need to reaffirm the
nation-state system to move in this
direction direction of resilience at
least initially in order to change
course are we looking at nation-states
as part of small world networks in the
u.s. we are talking about bio
regionalism as small centers of agency
than the nation in other words is the
nation-state an appropriate boundary
condition or constraint no it isn't and
I think actually if you look at Europe
the dominant cultures are still 14th
century cultures yeah I'm well sure yeah
we support anybody who's playing against
England it doesn't matter
yeah I mean yeah it's very simple as
long as the English balloons were happy
all right I have rugby shirts for every
nation which plays against the buggers
but I think if you look at your a blank
Word document from Paris but there is
radically different since a B and so on
the argument in Europe is what we
actually need is the European Union to
provide financial defence and foreign
policy but then you want smaller states
which do culture Europe is distorted by
the big states like Germany and France
yeah so the idea of and there is
actually a maximum size a state can get
to which is about five to seven million
there is a bit to come from the number
of cities before it loses cultural
coherence so if you look at it the
Scandinavian countries other than Sweden
have a lot of cultural coherence Sweden
doesn't because it's about 10 million
u.s. is far more I'm in Africa we just
completely buggered up by changing the
cultural boundaries with artificial
lines and there's still a conflict and
they need to go back to the original
these are still there right the state is
more problematic I mean we get a big
scenario planning exercise a few years
back and came out with a Handmaid's Tale
scenario which basically said what's
actually going to happen is that people
who live in red states in blue cities
will start to migrate to blue states
because they can't survive the
legislation yeah which means blue will
become bluer and red will become redder
and you get Gilyard and you can see that
happening and I think that's actually
you know accelerate yeah so you might
well get California Washington you know
you know Oregon but I mean Oregon is
completely split between Portland and
and the country right
so America has lost its cohesiveness
he's also lost its will leadership even
if you get rid of Trump you won't
recover it not not for some time
most European and Africa and Asia has
already done this they put their second
betting which I know Europe is going to
start doing the same so we're going to
face a radically different structure and
China's going to come out of this better
than anybody else because actually
they can make the hard decisions we've
now got a democratic system based on
one-person one-vote
which actually doesn't work one-person
one-vote evolved for small populations
with a highly resilient ecosystem it
doesn't work for large populations where
there's too much manipulation so I think
one of the things we need to start to
look at is smaller communities which
actually you know the people you're
electing and then those elect to the
larger groups and what's interesting is
if you go back to the American
Constitution they basically say you
can't elect some of the president by a
popular vote because we'll get
demagogues so they say every state
should elect some intelligent people who
get together and decide something
newsworthy be President and that was a
good idea then they mandated a delegate
so into the major international groups
and this is why it's so annoyed that
Britain's left Europe but I think they
might redeem that now actually there's
still hope that because Europe was a
democratic counter because America
hasn't been a democracy for the last
twenty years it's what in your British
politics would be called a rotten
borough yeah it's got all the
characteristics of a rotten borough
before the 1840 1812 reformat China
definitely isn't a democracy
um Africa is all over the place that in
America has got a lot of hope but if you
look at it we're now all talking about
downloads in tracker apps so we're all
about to become Chinese I'm not going to
download something with a centralized
database and now I can how it can be
misused yeah but people are starting to
accept that and Western governments are
leaping on the Chinese model now so I
think our real danger here is the wrong
sort of control you know people will
accept lis coming out of the crisis
Adam would you like to meet yourself and
ask a question sure just referring to
the diagram that you showed earlier the
distributed ethnography topography he
what would you say right now is the most
important adjacent possibility for a
dominant narrative needing to move into
it's going to be different by different
societies so America has got a real
problem I mean I was watching pictures
of Californians on beach beaches on the
weekend yeah you're second wave is gonna
be devastating yeah it's gonna be really
devastating right whereas yeah and
Europe I mean look at Germany Germany
did everything right they're now getting
another peak you'll be fast I mean I'm
in Berlin just for the context I see
that happening you get it so basically
you've had sixteen two weeks ago there
were 16 major mutations on the coded
virus and there's probably more by now
yeah
America is all over the place in terms
the way it's working so I think you know
you're going to have to have different
cultures the individualism of the states
is so dominant remember this is a
society where you know people take and
run seriously after puberty and that's
that's really very scary right so
individual freedom probably means a herd
immunity thing is about the only thing
which is going to work in the state you
won't get enough consensus falaka which
means you're not going to get trouble I
mean my wife isn't allowed to leave the
house until next year because she's
highly vulnerable with you know chronic
chronic immune disease problems that
means I won't go to the states in
November even if it's open these are the
risk of an infection and carry through
so I think you need each cultural group
is going to have to find its own
adjacent possible and that's actually
the fractality I may have mentioned
earlier it's the it's the ability to
look at your own position from the same
source nature of everybody else and work
out where you step next because
everybody's Direction is going to be
slightly different but the overall
system can be coherent as a result yeah
but I'll say the key things we need to
investigate I think and money is
rationing yeah I think that that's
absolutely vital because the
neoliberalism agenda is dominated
we need to get rid of behavioral science
in favor of real science
yeah behavioral science has become evil
yeah it's yankin it's not logic yeah and
if we can restore respect in science
that will also make a difference yeah in
terms of the way it works so those are
kind of like two of the things I'd
worked on and also I think we need to
find ways to allow communities to cohere
in the crisis so at the moment people
are too isolated it's not going to work
so the boundaries need to become a bit
more permeable but if a community gets
infectious we need to be able to isolate
them very quickly
excellent Sara would you like to meet
yourself and ask a question so in terms
of the contact tracing or tracking apps
I'm wondering if you see any way to use
that story and adjacent possible shifts
to move toward I put an example in the
chat of Nikki case presenting a type of
app set up that does not centralize like
personal info but he's was different
I've been having this fight for years I
mean the biggest computing disaster in
disaster in the history of government
procurement worldwide and that's a very
high bar was the British patient record
system and the reason it was wrong is
they actually created a centralized
database which meant he was doomed to
fail when I was on the IBM bid team for
this and I recommended a non-compliant
bid which meant they got thrown off the
bid team that we wrote it anyway and we
said what you should do is everybody
should carry their record with them
either on a credit card or an implanted
chip or a physical record if they're
going to die in the next five years
anyway why bother computerizing it and
you invest in common reader technologies
so you can actually your your the system
is always up to date somewhere on where
you are and that would have cost a small
amount of money to implement and we
actually did it in other countries the
same I think is true here
the trouble is the academics who
designed this sort of stuff yeah are
coming from a research perspective not a
human perspective so they want
everything in one place and so that they
can do stuff and they're not they're not
being realistic about this because I
think it needs 60 65 percent update to
work and there's already a Civil
Liberties campaign against it I think
the best nudge ominous to be honest
would be for Apple and Google to come
together and create one because they're
both arguing for distributed stuff if
Apple and Google created one and work
with Facebook that would that everybody
would use them and when I trust Apple on
confidentiality I don't trust Google but
I trust Apple all right as far as
anybody can be trusted but every state
is going down its own route which is
coming like crazy and the states which
are going down a centralized route you
only have to look at some of their
politics to see why they're doing that
but if anybody's got contacts yet - tech
giants to do it they could do it faster
and better than any of the others and
they could actually put social play
around there as well great and then I'm
just gonna ask this question on behalf
of Joe cuz I think it's an excellent one
to end on what resource would you point
to for people looking to learn about the
absolute basics of complexity science do
we start with math or computer science
is there a textbook there's actually
quite a good little box or all in going
if that's a lot of rides me going you
can read him if you write something in
part there's a wonderful book by ELISA
Guerrero but the first section is only
for philosophers she solves the problem
of when is a wink of not a blink which I
spent the year of my life working on
it's fascinating but the second part is
brilliant - papers are very good I
actually put a reading list up on the
website so behind me if you can see
apart from the you'll see in 20% of the
Starbucks City my collection then
there's another 10 meters of that around
the other walls but that bookcase behind
me has got the books I really wrote
which includes some poetry and other
stuff
so basically I got the zapper yeah this
is boys with toys and I scan the
barcodes and everything in that bookcase
and put it up on the web so there isn't
a single book at the moment particularly
on the yeah that's the right book bite
but I wasn't going but that'll give you
what we call computational complexity so
there's there's a big divide at the
moment this computational complexity
which is Santa Fe and they've gone down
that route heavy yeah there's complexity
as a metaphor which we all despise
because that's just put in old wine into
new wineskins it's the systems thinkers
rebadging using our language meg weekly
isn't particularly bad at that she uses
the language of complexity but she still
thinks she's in the cause of the
universe right
and then there's anthro complexity which
basically says you know this is a
transdisciplinary area and that's my
field and some of my colleagues and
other people but the book hasn't been
written there yet complexity is still
mainly articles yeah and when i've got a
whole bookshelf there i would say none
of the popular books i've read cause
anything other than revulsion all right
i mean they really are truly banned and
the trouble is the academic books are
really very very academic if they're any
good it is possible to translate the two
which I and others are working on the EU
handbook on how to manage a crisis will
be the first effort on that because
ultimately confessed he's actually quite
simple it's actually common sense the
trouble is you've got it and in three
decades of uncommon sense which is
polarized between what I call the New
Age fluffy Bernie it's all about
psychology and meditation and going um
in the morning all right
and the the rigid process guys yeah
everything is about process engineering
definition and you can see that by
cottony in business process
reengineering against learning
organization you know both of them own
valid because both they're only looking
at part of the solution
excellent and we're gonna wrap up thank
you so much Dave for coming in and
talking to us it was excellent and
there's so many more questions for us
hopefully we can see you again here at
the stove Oh always happy to come yeah
wonderful
so we're gonna cover some of the
upcoming sessions that we have we have
existential dance party later today
at 8:30 Eastern Time Colin Morris and on
Friday we have the psycho technology
playground with Nita Roy we also have
upcoming sessions Rayven you just
Benitez here you know we need to do you
want to unmute yourself and just maybe
talk a little bit about the psycho
technology kind of curious
exercises we're gonna work on power we
did trust last week we'll work on power
great and then later on today we have
human systems life action redesign with
Sarah Ness and and Lorraine silk and
that will be at 2:30 p.m. Eastern Time
so if you'd like to RSVP for any of the
future sessions visit us at the stoah
dot CA and the stove operates on a gift
economy so if you would like to give us
a gift we we would love to receive it
and we see the so as a gift for everyone
while we're moving through this
challenging time so if you would like to
support us you can visit us under the
gift economy tab
at the stoah Peter do you have anything
else you would like to say no just
thanks to Dave things to you Raven and
thanks for everyone with excellent
questions that was a wonderful session
great all right thank you all